Guide to the Jim Varney Collection of Advertising, 1983-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jim Varney Collection of Advertising 1983-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Carden and Cherry Advertising Agency, Inc.
2.1 linear feet Extent: 100 Items
Jim Varney was an actor who played the character Ernest P. Worrell in commercials, a television series (Hey Vern! It's Ernest), and numerous movies. These materials were collected and donated by Roy Lightner. The collection (2009-0119) (100 items; 2.1 lin. ft.; dated 1983-2000) includes videotapes of Ernest films; audiocassettes of commericals; advertising kits used to pitch Ernest as a spokesman for local markets; Ernest memorabilia, including t-shirts, movie posters, buttons, a towel, and a doll; and other miscellaneous marketing tools used by the Carden and Cherry Advertising Agency. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
RL.01328
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Jim Varney Collection of Advertising was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from Roy Lightner in 2009.
Historical Note
Jim Varney was an actor most famous for his portrayal of Ernest P. Worrell, a creation of the Carden and Cherry Advertising Agency in 1980. Ernest served as a spokesman for local markets on both radio and television: his commercials typically consisted of him encouraging his neighbor, Vern, to use whatever product the sponsor sold in that particular market. Clients varied, but included dairies, gasoline, local television stations, and car dealerships. Ernest was so well-received that a television series (Hey Vern! It's Ernest) and a series of movies were produced between 1987 and 1998. Varney died of lung cancer in 2000.
Collection Overview
The materials in this collection include 18 videotapes of various Ernest films; two audiotapes of Ernest pitches; five Ernest posters; t-shirts, a doll, a license plate, and other Ernest memorabilia and merchandising products; articles and other publicity materials; advertising kits from the Carden and Cherry Advertising Agency; testimonials from Ernest clients; and personal photographs from collector Roy Lightner with Jim Varney.
Subject Headings
Varney, Jim; Lightner, Roy; Carden and Cherry Advertising Agency, Inc.; Worrell, Ernest P. (Fictitious character); Posters; Videotapes; Audiocassettes
Contents of Collection
- Accession (2009-0119), (3 boxes)
  The collection (2009-0119) (100 items; 2.1 lin. ft.; dated 1983-2000) includes videotapes of Ernest films; audiocassettes of commericals; advertising kits used to pitch Ernest as a spokesman for local markets; Ernest memorabilia, including t-shirts, movie posters, buttons, a towel, and a doll; and other miscellaneous marketing tools used by the Carden and Cherry Advertising Agency.
  - Sales pitch portfolio (Box 1)
  - Sales kit (Box 1)
  - Roy Lightner family photographs with Ernest (Box 1)
  - Newspaper advertisements (Box 1)
  - Television spot scripts, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - National publicity; articles about Varney (Box 1)
  - Local publicity, 1984-1994 (Box 1)
  - Advertising photographs with products (Box 1)
  - News reports and obituaries, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
  - Merchandising items (Box 1)
    - Autographed photographs (Box 1)
    - Stickers (Box 1)
    - Greeting cards (Box 1)
    - Mask (Box 1)
    - Ornament (Box 1)
    - Beach towel (Box 1)
  - Client testimonials (Box 1)
  - Videotapes (Box 1)
    - Ernest Goes to Africa (Box 1)
    - Ernest Greatest Hits, Vol. 1-2 (Box 1)
    - Ernest Scared Stupid (Box 1)
    - Ernest Goes to Jail (Box 1)
    - Ernest Goes to Camp (Box 1)
    - Dr. Otto and the Riddle of the Gloom Beam (Box 1)
    - Hey Vern! It's my Family Album and Ernest 'n Vern's Greatest TV Hits, 1983 (Box 1)
    - The Ernest Film Festival: 101 Ernest and Vern Commercials and Bloopers, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Hey Vern! It's Ernest! School Daze (Box 1)
    - Hey Vern! It's Ernest! Holidays (Box 1)
    - Hey Vern! It's Ernest! Sports (Box 1)
    - Hey Vern! It's Ernest! Scary Things (Box 1)
    - Ernest in the Army (Box 1)
    - Ernest Rides Again (Box 1)
    - Ernest Goes to School (Box 1)
    - Hey Vern! Win 10,000...Or Just Count on Having Fun!, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Ernest P. Worrell news interviews, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Ernest/Sprite Sales Rally, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Ernest demo reel: Dairies, TV, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Posters (Box 2)
    - Dr. Otto and the Riddle of the Gloom Beam (Box 2)
    - Ernest Goes to Jail (Box 2)
    - Ernest Saves Christmas (Box 2)
    - Do I look like I have stupid written all over my face? (Box 2)
    - KnowhutImean? (Box 2)
  - Ernest doll (Box 3)
  - Ernest t-shirts (3) (Box 3)